The Babage difference engine was an example of
mechanical iteration where you make a motor or
a crank or something to do something. Um, one
of the earliest and most powerful mechanical
computers ever built was called the Bomba and it
was used to crack uh encrypted communications in
World War II with the Germans and Japanese that
used a device called the Enigma to encrypt these
message and send them using Morse code and
radio. And the Bomba was a British Polish
device that repeatedly tried to guess these
settings for a day, like guessing a password
based only on the encrypted text. And so when you
listen to a bomba moving, it is lots of clicking,
lots of spinning, and lots of uh rotation
because the iteration is kind of rotation.
[Applause]
So we we think of a for loop as iteration
but the in a physical computer a for loop
is often rotation. Another device that kind of
approximates this same kind of computation with
a little less high-end is a pinball machine.
So the Bomba was a very fast electromechanical
computer in the 30s and the 40s. Um, the pinball
machine is kind of like the 50s and the 60s,
and it's just it's a kind of a good example
of how uh state-of-the-art military technology
becomes games later because a pinball machine
uses switches and relays and physical storage
like piles of balls to track a score, award
free games, and count the number of balls,
start the games, stop the games, take your money,
and give you credits. And these are all built by
using relays and wiring and knowing things like
the response time of a relay when it's switching
from sort of off to on. And then relay feedback
that once a relay goes to on, it stays on.
[Applause] And in many ways it's a throwback to
the kind of technology that the electromechanical
computational technology similar to the bomba.
But the problem is that the pure mechanical
computations were just too slow. And if you take a
machine like the Babbage engine and you just make
it go 20 times faster, it's going to fall apart
in like less than a minute. might take you years
to build. You go too fast in it and all the pieces
come flying off. And that's because the the energy
to change the state, right? So changing state,
again, going back to this, the changing of the
state is me pushing on the thumb thing. But if
I all of a sudden made a really fast engine that
would push this thing a thousand times a second,
it would probably break. It couldn't take the
stress. And so the problem is is that physical and
electromechanical computing had just a limit of
there's like inertia you know physical problems
like inertia and so you can't you have to limit
the speed of like the difference engine so you
don't or the bomba so you don't just physically
damage the machine. If you go to the maximum
speed and double it you will break the machine
very very quickly. So what happened was is instead
of storing data and storing the zero or the one in
something mechanical like a relay, they started
using again in World War II at Bletchley Park
uh electronic switching using tubes. Now tubes
are uh interesting devices. They are generally
have a vacuum in them. And uh let me show you let
me show you this a little bit more closeup. So,
here's a tube, okay? And this is a vac. This
is glass. It has a vacuum in it. And there
are little plates in this tube that are heated up
and glow. And electrons flow between the plates.
There's a base and an emitter and then a grid that
speeds or slows up the electrons. And you know,
there's electric p electrics uh is sent in.
Sometimes it's heating. Sometimes it's sort of
just a positive or negative. Sometimes it's to
control it. Now the original idea of tubes was
to take sound waves from say a microphone and
amplify them to be louder to go to a speaker.
And so tubes are analog and continuous
amplifiers, meaning whatever you put in,
whatever signal you put in, could be a
sort of a flat signal or a moving signal,
it's going to come out louder, increased. What
happens is they can do some feedback in these
tubes and sort of tune them in such a way that
you can have a certain level of voltage that
is the zero and a certain level of voltage is
the one and then with a little feedback you
can make the zero and the one sticky. And so it
takes power and they generate heat but they have
no moving parts so they can switch way faster
than any kind of a physical storage device. So,
one of the first tubebased electronic computers
was called the Colossus, also at Bletchley Park,
currently at the National Museum of Computing
History um at Bletchley Park. But it could do the
other computations way faster than the electro
electromechanical computer called the Bomba.
But they're they're pretty hot. If you stand by
this thing, you can feel heat coming off of it.
Um power consumption and heat dissipation
for tubebased computers even though they're
much faster are still a challenge. This is an
electronic computer, the world's first computer
for many years because of the secrecy and it
assumed that the American computer was the
world's first computer. In fact, that's computer
Americans. This computer predated it by three
years, but nobody knew that. So this man who
designed and built the world's first electronic
computer went back to Dollar Hill and no one ever
heard of him. He carried on designing teleph.
But how do you build something that there were
no records? Well, not quite. How many flowers are
still alive? And he offered to help. Uh there were
still 89 black and white photographs uh in managed
to find some of the engineers who were still alive
and surprise surprise they had kept notebooks uh
that circuit check fragment up there had been kept
so they managed to get the bolt together in terite
and using a modern computer design package they
redesigned the cloth floor too from the ground
up having redesigned it I hope I'm not making any
mistakes that's right having designed the cluster
from the ground up uh of uh they had to build it.
This gentleman was clever enough uh real life the
telephone exchanges were decommissioning all their
own exchanges. He took a lorry went to the back
door and said I'll get rid of all that old scrap
and for free acquired the stock of values etc.
I believe they started with the uh the malware
the ground up in but a mere 14 years 15 years
of it 16 16 years they had a working machine but
to prove this is a rebuild this is not a model
or a simulation you need to make it do what it was
designed to do work out the to break the len cyper
machine now we had here a lorren machine they
were captured at the end of the war by the field
marshall tessering from Gil Marshall tessering
machine was sent to the hind store kiti museum in
porning Germany. They generated a test message,
intercepted here, printed across the tape,
put the tape on the routine. Three and a half
hours later via decrypted for that system. Okay.
Yeah. Heat.
Now going back to programming, a big subplot in
the hidden figures movie is the transition from
doing complex calculations manually by humans in a
room with adding machines to doing them by writing
portren programs on IBM. M790. This was NASA. And
the interesting thing is there's such a natural
parallel to writing forrren instructions to
following some written instructions by doing all
the calculations. And and it was very natural for
these people who had years of experience following
instructions precisely to then start writing for
train code that the computer would follow. And so
being au human computer was a natural training
ground for the emerging programming field.
The basic idea of this first phase is kind of
fun. We have built endless physical devices
over time to help us better understand our
world. Things like the passage of time,
things like the solar systems, stars in the night
sky, things like how fast you can go through air,
whether it's a boat or a airplane. Um,
we've always been interested in money.
things like curved motion under the
effect of gravity spacecraft like
in the movie Hidden Figures. There was a
lot of calculations that happened and the
uh by the way the IBM 7090 in Hidden Figures was
built using transistors solid state electronics
that greatly reduced heat and power consumption
and increased speed and they could do basically
24,000 multiplications per second. So in upcoming
lectures we're going to start exploring how we
go from relays and motors to solid state
computation. [Music] [Applause] [Music]